hello and welcome everybody this is
physics as information processing it's
October 28th
2023 and we're in discussion 6 so we'll
see where and how and when we go but to
begin with thank you for watching if
you're watching live please feel free to
write any questions or comments in the
live chat as this is our last discussion
we're going to be probably ranging
broadly so looking forward to people's
comments there otherwise perhaps we can
all go around first and say hello or
just give any thoughts or
Reflections to get things going and then
we'll jump into some of the questions
and answers and look at some of these
great thoughts that have
been sent and responded to so perhaps
Dean and then Harrison
David any just overall thoughts or
comments to get us
going um thanks Daniel I guess my
overall impression was that I think that
the way that the entire series was
organized and and and um structured
allowed for these kinds of conversations
that we're having today which I think
are really really valuable as as you can
see on the slide here I think a lot of a
lot of question and answer tends to be
focused around what
is um whereas the the conversations that
we've had uh we can sort of tease that
apart a little bit and ask questions
around what if and get into the
counterfactual piece of it and and
interact around that and I've really
really appreciated that so that's my
overall sense that we haven't left it
sort of on the
page um we've actually been able to sort
of breathe some life into it through
these
conversations oh
Harris yeah uh I just wanted to say that
it was a great series we all left a lot
and we got the opportunity to uh even
ask questions to um to Chris and uh get
back some very insightful
answers uh that they are very helpful in
order to uh let's say push the envelope
forward uh overall this has been a a
great uh series I've enjoyed it a lot
and while conversing with some of my
colleagues uh they also enjoyed it so uh
the feedback is is great and uh thanks
to activ inference Institute for
facilitating this and to you
guys thank you thank you and welcome
David if you want to just begin with any
thoughts or what brought you into the
game in the bottom of the
ninth
um well in in school I was actually
trying
to use um free energy to develop some
sort of a network of agents that were
deciding what information to send and
what states to be in based on each
other's approximation of each other's
States and um so I registered at the
beginning but then I guess life happened
I didn't really crash the
page but
um yeah so now I'm just kind of opening
up to things and participating more in
the world that I exist in and this is a
natural um this is really tied to to the
work that I was doing in
school I don't know if this is a place
to ask a question so I'm not going to
asking any question but that's like the
let's begin with
that okay oh yeah so I was thinking
about I was qu I was I'm still confused
about like Markoff blankets and non-
localism how would those two things work
together well like non- localism seems
to me that an entity could be
distributed arbitrarily in uh like in
whatever is I don't know if the universe
say like SpaceTime is what is or if
that's just a construction that we
create through the information
processing and like putting relation
like enunciating or like uh rendering
the information in a way where it's like
all the related components can be
mutually
distinguished um but the Markoff blanket
seems to be highly local I I don't know
maybe I this is what but like I'm
confused about this it seems to be
highly local and like uh it seems like
everything is connected with everything
um so I I'm kind of confused about how
an entity could be defined with a
Markoff blanket while at the same
time what is seems to be completely
intertwined non-local
mutually like
defined yes Dean please so can I just
just clarification are you thinking that
local and non-local
is um somehow similar to maybe
arbitrary
um I'm thinking local is like within a
volume and non-local is like distributed
like a loc like a sphere like a small
sphere where all the information is like
within a sphere and everything within
that sphere is causally relevant
everything without is causely irrelevant
but
then um like a I'm thinking of a markof
market as a sphere and everything on the
inside is like independent statistically
from everything on the outside I guess
I'm asking around when where where do
you play where do you see that being
placed do you see that being placed
arbitrarily like when you when you set
that up whenever you whenever you decide
where that bound re exists are you
asking because it's local or it's
non-local because it's wherever inside
and
outside is present is is it is the is
the is
the what's the word I'm looking
for are you are you are you wondering
about how the how that doesn't seem to
be consistent that it one minute it can
be here and then the next minute it can
change in arbitrarily end up being in a
different
place not not that I'm not that it
doesn't seem to me that that's the
confusion it's more
like
um like you know David bom's implicate
and explicate order and the idea that
the explicate order is like one hologram
there's like the hollow movement where
each layer affects each layer and it's
all the explicate is all at once
explicated in mutual relatedness I don't
know
um I don't know if these words are
incoherent
completely like uh and uh
um and then but the but then the uh
markof blanket like I'm I'm taking the
example of my skin as like I don't know
if that's
even um good example but my skin is like
a markof blank kid but but then if
everything is mutually related and
explicated like this whole body is
submerged in the same field that
everything else is submerged in and in
that sense everything is linked to
everything there's no I don't know
like
um let me try adding a few pieces here
so welcome welcome Ander and and Chris
will hopefully join too here we
go okay opening act
just to catch up Chris and Ander David
asked about the marov blanket and
about if slow everything is connected to
everything and how we associate Marco
blanket or the holographic screen with
localism and
non-locality do you want to give any
quick thoughts on this or are you asking
me if you want to either of you could um
I don't know uh let's wait a minute for
Chris to show up uh yeah I'm I'm here
now yeah I'm glad you found the way
finally so uh did you guys question did
you guys go through the slides of last
time the lecture on biology no no we
just began and started with a mar
blanket
question yeah um I mean I think I think
it wouldn't hurt to talk about that
because um a big part of of that last
lecture was the copy and diversified
notion um as a universal feature in
nature
and I mean naively I'm I I think that
you know the creation of new boundaries
is implicit in there so maybe maybe
Chris can comment but
I I also thought it was very worthy of
mentioning today that you know the cycle
of error correction memory and so on so
th those would be my only two comments
in in the agenda for today uh maybe
Chris can say a few words but I didn't
mean to interrupt uh so Marco blankets
we can pivot it to biology I'm sure okay
okay I think I'm seeing this question is
this a question about the definition of
Markov blankets I there's there's
something about I I can't actually see
the
entire no it's not a question on my
screen oh it's not a question on your
screen okay a question on your
screen right but could you tell me what
the question is again yeah David just
restate it how you see
it well the question was if
um if everything is like mutually
connected and mutually defined and
interconnected and there's a non-
localism in the sense that everything is
mutually connected and mutually find and
um I'm kind of
implicitly working with assumption that
the implicate explicate order uh makes
sense and they explic it is like one
hologram and it's all lost audio Al
together
now
um oh I still hear
him oh the audio
Chris Chris can you is audio okay yeah
yeah I lost at least half that audio
just dropped out Al together oh yeah so
I'll try to sorry about that I I'll just
like so if if everything is kind of
explicated like if it's information in
the brain is kind of rendering it all at
once together I'm just confused as and
the whole body is submerged in the same
like in the same like the whole body is
submerged in it like if I look in the
mirror the whole body is submerged in it
and it's all uh non-local I mean by that
I mean it's all like connected together
and mutually defined and mutually uh
necessary to even make sense of any
piece of it uh if there is even such a
thing as a pie and I'm wondering I mean
not so that's one that's one way of
looking at it and then the other way is
like the local to me it seems like the
there's like the skin Markoff blanket
it's kind of local and I'm kind
of like confused as to how those things
uh kind of work like how those
things
like it seems like all the information
in a sphere a sphere could be a Markov
blanket and then the on the inside and
the outside they're statistically
independent is that the like the the
whole movement on the inside and the
outside because of the markof blanket
separates those but then if everything
is this whole body is submerged in this
thing that's mutually related I just
confused as to
how
like I don't know I just I'm confused as
how those things work
together um
I I sus I suspect the I'm not sure I
understand your question but I suspect
the answer has to do with whose point of
view we're talking
about so if if you are the system that's
in so let's fix a marov blanket
someplace uh if you're the system on the
inside then all you can see is what's
encoded on the blank
and you have no independent access to
what the Dynamics is on the outside so
you don't actually know what the
Dynamics is on the
outside um and similarly if you're on
the
outside now if you're somehow able to
view the whole system you can see the
whole system is having some joint
Dynamics but if the if the whole system
is is is olated then there isn't anybody
on the outside kind of by
definition so the idea of a whole
Dynamics is just a theoretical postulate
that we make to make the mathematics
make
sense now if you move
to a move from the classical formulation
to the quantum
formulation then it's possible to prove
a very nice theorem which is that if
you're
inside uh a holographic
screen uh you can't measure the
entanglement entropy across the
screen uh what that means is that you
can't know that your state is
conditionally independent of what's
going on outside so you if if you're
inside a holographic screen you can't
know that you're not entangled with with
whatever's
outside so you can't even know whether
you have uh a well-defined state in a
sense and I'll sort
of I think the same thing would probably
hold true from the point of view inside
a Markov blanket that uh you wouldn't be
able to know whether your Markov blanket
had holes in it or something like that I
mean the the problem is in the classical
formulation uh you assume there's no
analog of
entanglement uh so there's no analog of
entanglement
entropy so I think the strongest thing
you can say is you don't actually know
your statistical relationship to what's
going on outside but you still can only
see what's encoded on the
blanket thank you Chris if I can add a
few more pieces so David you described
everything connected to everything for a
system with that kind of a base graph
there aren't Markov blankets because a
Markov blanket is the set of nodes that
make two other sets of nodes
conditionally independent so in a fully
connected
setting again be leading to the question
what is outside of that but in a fully
connected setting you don't have a
blanket as such um in fact the basian
graph describes the factorization or the
articulation and the sparsity of the
system so it is a
connectedness that is usually much much
much sparser than everything connected
to everything but that's not to say that
differences can't make a difference at a
distance it's just that they propagate
through a local causal structure and
then SpaceTime is constructed by certain
kinds of cognitive agents that was one
of the key aspect aspects of this
course and so we can take as
primary the topology of the active
inference agent environment
relation
and then marov
blanket is just the sensorium on the
inbounds and the action capacity on the
outbound one question though I do have
to that is what about the
nonzero gravitational effect for example
of something that's
distant in space and
time of course Markov blankets don't
have to be spatial temporal they can be
an arbitrary State
spaces but how do we deal with those
kinds of long
range
influences that's that's my question
yeah well uh here I think it's useful to
contrast Newtonian gravity with with
einsteinian
gravity uh Newtonian gravity is infinite
range and instantaneously
acting whereas einsteinian
gravity is infinite range but it's
locally
encoded so
uh Einstein the einsteinian gravity that
you
feel
is
your local measurement of the curvature
of your local bit of
SpaceTime so that is very much happening
on on your Markov blanket right it's a
local measurement uh local in SpaceTime
so let's let's assume There's A
Spacetime that's objective and
characterizes everything
uh then you're locally measuring it on
your blanket and that's what you feel as
as gravitational attraction or or your
mass uh whereas in uh Newtonian or lassi
and
gravity uh you don't have that sense of
locality right as soon as something
changes anywhere in the universe it
affects
you so Einstein was
was struggling of course to make gravity
consistent with electromagnetism where
it was clear that forces are transmitted
at at finite speed the speed of light
and he didn't have the idea of a
graviton moving at the speed of light uh
but he did have this this idea of local
measurement so non-locality was was a
NAA to to Einstein and that's basically
why he spent so much trouble removing it
from
physics and that's why he hated the idea
of entanglement so much because it
seemed to him that from a space time
point of view it had to be non
local Daniel can I bring up a point at
this point so I think uh this is
somewhat relevant to uh a question I
really wanted to ask Chris which is in
lecture six I remember minute 23 I I
wish I had written it down but I can
roughly remember
um it was you know that philogenetic
graph and and you see life
growing in a self-similar way you know
just like the the the genealogical tree
of species same thing happens at the
individual level with growth and so on
anyways I found that fascinating in the
sense that the degrees of
freedom of Life as a whole grow right
and and around that minute 23 you made a
comment well then the environment must
must be shrinking and you tie this with
SpaceTime and something about SpaceTime
you know we from the physics side we
also have that uh you know we have
cosmological inflation and whatnot are
any of those things related that that
remark uh I feel like was made in
passing and I think there's a lot there
to to be said um it also maybe shed some
light
on uh the Emer SpaceTime issue if it
does uh emerge from a more basic
ontological object like a tensor Network
and the the degrees of freedom at in the
tensor network is it fair to say that
life as it grows gets more of those
degrees of freedom but then
somehow anything that happens to
SpaceTime is an illusion in that sense I
don't even know if I'm formulating that
question right but I I think Chris knows
what's what I'm talking
about yeah I the the the comment makes
the most sense in uh the context of the
the state space itself leaving a s side
State uh SpaceTime so if you think of uh
think of a Hilbert
space and uh draw a boundary
someplace that separates what what we're
going to call life from what we're going
to call
non-life yeah and uh essentially what
you know life has done over the past
three billion years is incorporate bits
of the non-life part of the state space
into life right so so you know total
biomass is increasing right uh so more
and more of the available mass is
getting incorporated into living things
and so if we we can kind of heris fold
SpaceTime in and
say
uh you know in the in the in the
locality in the local of Earth and over
this fairly short time period uh and the
expansion of SpaceTime is is more or
less
negligible um so so life is actually
taking up more space
now that it
did certainly at the time of lucco when
all of us uh weren't around but there is
just one probably population of cells
that we're descendants
of
uh but the the point about the the hbert
space is is just is just the point that
if you have once if you've divided it in
two and you move the boundary then one
system gets bigger at the expense of the
other system which now has less of the
hbert
space so that's all that
remark really is
right as the
system uh in a sense takes over degrees
of freedom of the of the environment so
that's in that case it becomes a
different system at every time step from
the point of view of it it has now a
different Hilbert space and different
internal Dynamic so physically it's a
different thing yeah but when when we
look at it we say oh this thing is
continuous through time it it is
expanding it's growing it's developing
evolving
whatever right and so so then I guess
comment just that uh question that just
occurred as you as you were talking that
begs the question uh you know does that
biomass come to dominate all the uh
degree degrees of freedom in the
universe is that there's all presumably
there's a tension with the rate at which
that those degrees of freedom are
growing and the rate at which SpaceTime
is growing does the growth of SpaceTime
in terms of those degrees of freedom
that may be more fundamental uh amount
to loss in error correction
capacity uh how how do we not I mean and
maybe more spec speculatively how you
reconcile this with uh loss of
thermodynamics like it do we know are
you implying that life is going to come
to dominate every everything and fill up
the entirety of of the known
universe um yeah I I think that's a
stretch U
but
um I would say at this point that until
we have a a a mature theory of quantum
gravity that makes enough empirical
predictions to be
testable uh it's not clear at least to
me how the
whole emergent SpaceTime picture fits
together with uh the inflationary
picture or the expanding SpaceTime
picture
um I mean in some sense taking a strict
cobbert space view
if the universe is an isolated
system then it's Hilbert's face is
fixed and so your
question in a sense becomes what's the
relationship between SpaceTime and this
Hilbert space are are what we think of
as SpaceTime degrees of freedom real
degrees of freedom or
not and uh um seems to me that question
really isn't resolved and I I'm not sure
at this point how to resolve
it Aris you wan to yeah just um have
some something small to add um overall
this is uh very interesting and uh these
questions are very deep uh what I wanted
to add is that I was uh uh thinking the
initial question regarding Mark of
blankets and I also have some question
that uh it's related with it but I will
ask a chis later uh what I wanted to add
now is that um basically Mar Mark of
blankets are a way of describing the
boundaries of a system in terms of
statistical mechanics or statistics
let's say and uh essentially from what I
understand they are um um Paramount in
order to Define observers and also the
systems under
observation so any pH any physical
system that can be seen as an
observer uh with a mark of blanket let's
say so uh now trying to tie it all up
with active
inference well active inference as I
understand it it implies that the system
uh is actively referring to um its
external States from its internal States
in an effort to both uh uh learn let's
say and adapt to the uh to the
environment so uh this goes back and
ties with this metaphorical lingl say
with the skin this is how I I understand
it and uh it actually means that uh a
system with a mark of blanket can
actually be seen as performing physics
as information processing which is the
back of this series that uh chis is
offering to us and a final comment in
terms of non locality nonlocality can
actually be seen as a form of
information processing so this is what I
want n
part did you say uh how nonlocality is a
form of information
processing yes this is how I understand
this what do you think about about that
Chris
if
we put it in terms of
[Music]
entanglement
uh
entanglement is a useful resource for
information
processing but it's only a use a usable
resource if it's combined with classical
communication
either across time
or uh across
space
so um entanglement is only useful as of
as a
resource if different observers
can
act
locally uh I.E without interfering with
each
other on the Quantum
resource
so
um if you think of entanglement as
non-locality if you embed it in
SpaceTime in that
way
then it it is useful as a computational
resource but The Observers also have
to
transmit classical
Communications in a way that uh fully
complies with locality so in a in a bell
epr type experiment for example if you
have Alice in one lab and Bob in the
other lab making measurements of of some
entangled State then at some
point uh to know that the state is
entangled they have to send their CL
classical records to each
other uh as classical communication and
then deal with those records
locally so in a
sense nonlocality in that sense is
useful for computation but it's only
useful if you also have
locality great great thank you ER
actually I'm working on on uh
on a Noel notion let's say U um that
it's something like U takes the notion
of ENT tlement and transform it in in in
the following sense I'm I'm actually
thinking of Maximum un tanglement as a
resource for classical computation
so uh that's something I am actually
exploring it's I find it to be an uh
nice
concept did you say maximum
unentangled yes maximum separability
yeah okay that that makes sense I mean
we need maximum
separability yeah or or we need to be
able to factor a state space to talk
about two different
observers so to talk about conditional
Independence yeah in in in my head uh
these maximum entaglement as a resource
can actually be expended to perform
classical computation or even to
increase the coherence of a Quantum
system so I'm playing with that notion a
bit
who thank
you can I ask something really quick
about yeah there was uh okay
um so there apparently like from what I
don't understand very much but from um
bore apparently the
the the whole experimental setup was one
like
entity they couldn't
be broken down into like constituent
pieces that are interacting but had to
be taken as one entity from what I
understand and apparently Einstein's
view is
um well I really don't know what his
view was but apparent like it's not one
entity can broken be broken down to
localized pieces that are
interacting and I'm kind of apparently
they couldn't get along like Bor and
Einstein apparently there was like a
party or something and then they all
congregated to separate parts of the
room and didn't really
interact and apparently it was because
they had these like opposing views on
the same thing of like breaking down the
interconnectedness into separate
constituent subsystems and even like
taking the partial Trace I mean par
there was one universal function taking
the partial Trace which buzzly Define
the subsystems but never perfectly so
like it's all tied together but I can't
really exp I'm trying to say like how do
you um I'm
asone
like these seem like two very opposed
view they seem like very alternative
views like on on one side you have
like kind of like an indivisible ho and
the other side you have like locality
where it's almost like there's like a
sequence of measurements leading up to
an ego an I that then measures as like a
real
entity as another one is like the
Observer and The observed are one thing
they cannot be meaningfully
separated maybe functionally they can be
separated but like as actually onto like
as actually existing subcomponents that
cannot be defined strictly that's two
different I from what I understand one
of them is saying yes you can Define
these subsystems and they really do
exist as separate entities the the other
one is saying that's just kind of like
a like a useful notion like a useful way
to organize information as to operate on
that information deposit a subject and
an object and to have the subject
operate on the object is a useful way
for thinking to separate itself and it
seems like this is closer to Bor and the
other one is closer wellar apparently
that's a distinction of like Bor and
Einstein from what I understand uh from
what I understand which is please
correct me if it's wrong and uh so yeah
I want to put that out there and uh I
don't know what that's gonna Spa in
terms of responses but yes well I think
that's a a fair characterization of the
bore Einstein debate
actually to add a response there whether
it actually exists it seems like in one
of those framings you had an observer
looking at something and if we Define
actually existing in a relational
observed setting then to the Observer it
actually the measurement actually exists
prepare measure prepare measure and then
from another perspective viewing that
setup then it's the Observer of a
setup MH and so it's just again to
Chris's first point about what
perspective
and this is one of the most essential
pieces that that the blanket screen
relationality brings into play is there
isn't a view from nowhere but there is a
perspective that may have a definite
answer and yet there are multiple
perspectives that have complimentary
answers in our
scenario Daniel can I speak for a minute
oh yeah I was I was muted earlier I
didn't realize I meant to ask David I
don't have an answer to to your question
but uh I was wondering if you could
reformulate it would be would it be fair
to reformulate your question and say as
saying are blankets objective or not is
is the bore Einstein debate equivalent
to that and then second and I guess this
may be for for Chris I was skiping
through the answers and one of
them was talking about how the the main
one of the big tensions between general
relativity and quantum theory is the
idea of object persistence and I I I
don't know how to articulate it either
but I I feel like uh it was more or less
what you were getting at uh David is is
that is that
correct yeah I think that's a another
way to put it and and also the thing you
said about the third person looking at
those systems if there's multi-agent
communication that's what that's that's
kind of the thing that I'm that's kind
of the thing that I'm kind of stuck on
in terms trying to understand
this because like if there's a third
agent looking okay those two are
subsumed in the information on the
holographic
screen and then I don't know anyways so
that's where I'm kind
of I think a delightful thing to read
here is uh Jean viger's paper where he
introduces the vigner friend thought
experiment and I think it's from
uh there's a book called The Scientist
speculates the editor is someone named
good go
D
and uh it's also and vigner has a paper
in this book I think it's
1961 and it's also the paper where
vigner talks about uh Consciousness
being an essential Concept in quantum
theory but the the thought experiment is
uh
that viger's friend is doing an
experiment in his laboratory and making
observations um and vigner is outside
the
laboratory and um vigner has to regard
his friend is in some sort of
superposition with his instrument he has
to regard his friend as as entangled
with his friends
instruments uh until vigner can actually
interact locally with the friend and
make a measurement of the friend's
State and so it it makes
uh viger's friend and his
apparatus look like an entangled pair
and vigner now looks like an
experimenter who's operating on just one
part of an entangled
pair uh but vigner uh himself tells the
story very
nicely and it's just it's that sort
of historical text I think is is always
useful to have a look at and see how the
people
themselves were responding to this
idea and vigner is quite perplexed by
this thought
experiment
uh and I and I think all of those people
were were were quite you know they were
quite honestly mystified with what
observation actually is and what
uh Consciousness is and all of these
other questions that people are a little
bit scared to talk
about uh in the ensuing several
decades self
reference
yeah you can go
ahead self- reference seems to
be like there's this ancient symbol of
the uro
boros uh the output is the input it
feeds on itself even like Consciousness
I have to contextualize my I have to
contextualize to contextualize like a
self-referential I have to everything
refers to itself and then at the end
self- reference is where all the
paradoxes are like this sentence is
false or all I know is I know nothing
these are all paradoxical
statements so there's some sort of
mystery cell division of self- reference
like that ancient view is that it's like
embryogenesis cosmogenesis same
thing
um I don't know there's yeah there I it
seems to me that there's some sort of
mystery that's so it's like the M it
just eludes like I don't know thinking
tries to make these thought systems but
it just slips out like I don't it just
you can't grasp it I don't know
um I mean but that's that's already a
conclusion which I don't necessarily
want to even make because if it's self-
reference I is thinking okay then maybe
it goes all the way to the bottom but I
don't
know Daniel can I ask a question before
we run out of time actually I have two
maybe one is a bit longer the second one
is sh so the first one uh Chris is I was
very intrigued and looking forward to
hear you talk a little bit about that uh
Psych
of error correction and memory and you
know persistence and so on and in
particular uh I was wondering if it
relates at all to the main know the
thing you talked about in that lecture
six uh the copy and
diversify uh business because
intuitively if that cycle is something
that an organism has to implement I'm
talking about that that that slide with
you know the error correction and
whatnot then it pays a thermodynamic
price for it
uh so I presumably there's an anabolic
process of of of trying to grow so you
can feed degrees of freedom into this
error correcting scheme if you know
thinking like a physicist something like
that might be happening uh so is the
copy and
diversify feature a necessity of having
to run this cycle that's um my first
question
I that's a good question I don't know
whether it's
necessary
uh I think one could think of
a a fairly
smallscale heat engine or metabolic
system
that can pull just enough free energy
out
of its environment
to store a one bit
memory
uh and you can think of think of
something like a flip-flop right these
things aren't alive so it's not it's not
quite as complex as an
organism
but it it is using energy to maintain a
memory and its memory does influence Its
Behavior so I I think we have these
limiting cases like this that
don't have to
grow but when you when you think about
organisms
um organisms
have the problem of being made out of
very delicate parts that need to be
replaced and it's it's that degradation
that I think is driving this need for
constant
copying and for
from a physics point of
view I think what that boils down to is
that
the the organisms living right at the
edge of an interaction with its
environment that's too strong to
maintain so the the environment
environmental interaction
is constantly a risk of spinning out of
control and having too large an energy
transfer which basically tears the mark
on blanket
apart and exposes too many of the
internal degrees of freedom to the
outside so I this
this may be one way of of saying what
characterizes life that it's it's
interacting with its
environment right on the edge of an
interaction that's too
strong and it's it's it's great to have
a strong interaction because then you
have you have big I good values and so
you have large
bandwidth uh but the risk is that the
environment tears you
apart
close to the fire but don't get
burnt become become the fire and then
control the redo
balance and gain that autopoetic
regulative
capacity which works when it works yeah
until something comes along with bigger
teeth you
know um another comment if I May is um
as as the course comes to an end one two
of the two things I realized Associated
to classicality that we've talked a lot
about in this class
are object persistence and boundaries
right so so classicality being a
feature intrinsically boundary related
and having a lot to do with object
persistence and so so so artist just
thinks completely dual from from an FP
point of view you because you want to
maintain the Integrity of the
boundary you want you know you want to
preserve that classical information
presumably I'm not sure I guess my
question to to everyone is our object
persistence and uh and
uh well in the topic of uh classicality
object persistence and boundaries
like are are these basically completely
dual dual pictures that my
question yeah I wouldn't be
surprised and we also need object
persistence to define
space
so this idea of object persistence is
is a a very key idea that that has to be
dealt with and and physics has largely
ignored this idea which
is kind of objects are taken for
granted but but I think I think what
Carl says in that
2019 free energy principle for a
particular physics paper is fairly clear
on this I mean he basically
says uh the free energy principle tells
systems to
persist that's basically what a system
has to
do by by maintaining the Integrity of
its mark on
blanket I I think that's very
insightful if it doesn't it's
not yeah it's not a system
anymore well as
we
somewhat Glide towards a local closure
of course anyone is welcome to bring up
any
Reflections and
also I'd love to hear
about where we go from this now
measured
outcome how do we prepare individually
at The Institute scale ecosystem
scale and what are we going to do coming
out of
this are we talking about that right
now or any thoughts yeah just keep
learning
bro what do you mean by the ecosystem
scale like the active inference
ecosystem and our own
ecosystems going beyond our own scale I
guess the only thing I can comment on
this is I Echo The View that or not view
or or rather remark that Chris made in
the lecture about Quantum biology as a
field it's in a nent stage right now but
I mean I think you know there will be a
non trival interaction between the
active influence community and and
Quantum biology that I'm making that
suris right
now
so let's talk about Quantum biology for
a
second I'll open up the Pandora's Box
here let's think of it as a parable as a
post or maybe even fanfiction because
Chris has shared so much with us I I
want to kind of build off of it if you
will um indulge me for a second I'll
read you a little story just hear the
story
out qu Quantum biology sounds like more
than up or down without saying that it
is
more up or down as what information can
be counterfactually is looking at
carrying capacity as in quotes can
be and from that carrying capacity comes
orientation things like Direction and
scale things like the ability to plan
appear to fit better in the inter
orientation category relative to the
carrying capacity category which is
non-c communitive in
action so if and this is a big if if we
agree that orientation is to
follow should our recognizing of
planning affordances follow as well so
from the session slide there was a quote
living systems are genetic Quantum
systems that the fbp has driven of a
high level of computational complexity
and here the in quotes computation is
baked in as something planable
with this as a reference frame to make
plans we need carrying capacity check
agreed but in order to
learn where does the carrying capacity
Plus orientation relationship insist
that we start with a received
plan this perspective is compared to say
actively inferring our way to the plan
falls out of carrying
capacity just making this explicit we
can then ask should we first apply a
received plan or apply active
inference that helps clarify when the
strategy is one more based on
exploitation versus a strategy more B
based biased to exploration in summary
when did information delivery things
like product or package
packaging begin to Trump information
carrying capacity which is essentially
information processing rather than we
need this paired relationship the
carrying capacity Plus the orientation
as a minimum of two so that we can
compare identify change and no change
model patterns
Etc this is another way of asking when
did subject matter expertise come to be
seen as more valuable than prediction
matter expertise when it seems like when
you both capacities if we want
independency and here's the kicker if
not given time to reflect on what's
being asked here and I know Chris
oftentimes has a nice long pause to
reflect but if not given the time to
reflect people will take their subject
matter expertise
strategy which clearly is a next move
perspective over one that holds up next
move plus all moves meaning that they
bring prediction matter expertise in to
follow
to param parameterize to unlock to
unring to Unbound what's in and what's
out of course without prediction matter
expertise what is quantum
biology wow can you just post that
someplace so we can think of a I'll just
I'll just email it to you Chris
cool that was great
yeah I I I think you're you're asking
about
the fundamental question of what what
what does Carl call it epistemic value
and the role of curiosity and that whole
cluster of
issues well I I think I need to give you
the credit that you deserve on this I
think it's the fact that you have
allowed us to interact with you that's
given us the that kind of courage and
confidence to be able to put things out
there I don't know how much of it sticks
for how much of it I'm not sure that it
requires disciples but I do think it
provides what you've done is provided
that
Medium so again I guess that's my way of
saying thank you well thank you that's
that's
yeah thank you Chris uh I have learned
so much this year um more than more than
ever
before okay well great this is this has
been a great class and hopefully
uh hopefully various things will come
out of it I mean so certainly just from
looking at the questions that have been
in the question Forum lots of people are
thinking about these issues
and um that's that's what I think aii
needs going forward is people thinking
and talking about
stuff thank you Chris yeah a few
outcomes that we know we'll transcribe
the lectures the discussions add in
screenshots add in the Q&A and publish
those proceedings as a book we will pick
back up in
2024 with potentially having the
recorded and written contents as part of
a
curriculum so not just
replicating but now continuing on with
another quantum flow across this now
classical artifact
because it's Quantum in the moment and
then once it's
communicated it becomes a
classic and we have M to prepare that
state all right great I I'm gonna have
to sign off um but thank you very much
thank you Chris thank you thank you
Chris right
ciao does anyone
else does any anyone else want to make
any reflection or
comment I just thank everybody that's
helped
organize participated in all of the
discussions even the people who showed
up at the very end of the discussions
because I really appreciate that again I
can't emphasize enough when we get a
chance to interact with this stuff when
we get to manipulate it when we be able
to get ask questions even though we feel
vulnerable I think that that's when a
lot of the really good stuff um tends to
get Consolidated so thank you to all of
you I'll read some fun comments from the
live chat just the last several just to
recognize some of our great um
colleagues um lucrative
leadership um
wrote yes on yes more on affordances Ian
wrote would love for this series to
continue Joanne wrote thank you this was
a wonderful learning experience Mills
8102 wrote the probable and the possible
there's some emojis Pablo senta heart
powwow da I don't speak this language
but I can definitely hear understand and
feel it so thank you everybody who's
watching along these were all great and
um we prepare and measure every day at
The Institute so I really do hope that
people from all backgrounds all vectors
all preference and prior sets come Eng
gauge and not presuppose too much about
us or themselves or what can happen when
we really do interact and when we take
it
into the kinds of spaces and timelines
that we know we want to be
on all right thank you by bye thank you
everyone
bye